片名：雾都孤儿
给各位理事鞠躬
Bow to the board.
就是这孩子
This is the boy.
在救济院出生，然后去了教区农场
Born here in the workhouse. Moved to the parish farm.
现年9岁，已经到该回来的年纪了
Nine years old today. Time to be moved back here.
你叫什么，孩子？
What's your name, boy?
- 奥利弗・忒斯特 - 什么？
-OIiver Twist. -What?
- 那孩子是个傻子 - 孩子，听我说
-That boy's a fool. -Boy. Listen to me.
我想，你知道自己是孤儿吧？
You know you are an orphan, I suppose.
- 你说什么？ - 这孩子是个傻子，可能早就是了
-What's that? -The boy is a fool. I thought he was.
你知道你无父无母...
You know you've got no father or mother...
...由教会养大，是吗？
...and that you were brought up by the parish, don't you?
- 是的，先生 - 你哭什么？
-Yes, sir. -What are you crying for?
我希望你每天晚上都做祷告
I hope you say your prayers every night.
替那些养育你，照顾你的人祈祷
Pray for those that feed you and take care of you...
...像一个基督徒...
...Iike a Christian.
- 是的，先生 - 好吧...
-Yes, sir. -Well...
...你上这儿来是接受教育...
...you have come here to be educated...
...来学一门有用的手艺的
...and to be taught a useful trade.
这些东西放哪儿？
Here, where do you want these?
跟你旁边的孩子学
Learn from the boy next to you.
- 学什么，先生？ - 学拣麻絮
-What am I to Iearn, sir? -Learn to pick out the oakum.
麻絮是什么，先生？
What's oakum, sir?
你哪儿来这么多问题？！
Stop asking so many questions.
麻絮是从旧绳子里面挑出来的纤维
Oakum's the fibers you unpick from the old rope.
能再次用在女王陛下的船上
Then it's used again for the ships of Her Majesty's navy.
你是在为国效力
You're serving your country.
好了，干活吧
Now, get on with it.
汤姆，歇一歇好不好？ 我们还要睡觉呢
Tom, give it a rest, will you? We're trying to sleep.
- 睡不着，太饿了 - 我们都饿
-Can't sleep, too hungry. -We're all hungry.
是的，但我怕
Yes, but I'm frightened.
怕？为什么？
Frightened? Why?
什么？什么？
Why? Why?
我太饿了，我怕把旁边的小子吃了
I'm so hungry, I'm frightened I might eat the Iad that sleeps next to me.
主啊...
O Lord God...
...感谢你赐予我们...
...for the blessing of this generous and bountiful meal...
...如此丰盛的食物...
...that thou hast placed before us...
...感谢您的慷慨，阿门
...we give thanks. Amen.
阿门
Amen.
对不起，先生，我还要一点
PIease, sir. I want some more.
什么？
What?
对不起，先生，我还要
PIease, sir, I want some more.
快把执事找来！
Fetch the beadle!
尼姆金斯先生
Mr. Limbkins.
请原谅，先生
I beg your pardon, sir.
奥利弗・忒斯特还想要
OIiver Twist has asked for more.
还要？！
For more?!
镇静，邦布尔先生 清楚地回答我
Compose yourself, Mr. Bumble, and answer me distinctly.
你是说他吃了他的晚餐之后还要？
Do I understand that he asked for more after he had eaten his supper?
是的，先生
He did, sir.
那孩子以后准会被绞死
That boy will be hanged.
“5镑一个孩--”
"Five pounds and a b--"
我说“哇”，那就是“哇”
When I says "whoa," I means "whoa"!
“健...健康的...
"Health-- Healthy...
...学...学徒
...appren-- apprentice.
5镑”
Five pounds."
扫烟囱是个脏活
Chimney sweeping is a nasty trade.
以前有小孩在烟囱里面憋死的
Young boys have been smothered in chimneys before now.
那是因为要他们下来 可还没有点火...
That's because they damp the straw afore they Iight it in the chimney...
...他们就把稻草弄湿了 湿的稻草会生烟
...to make them come out again. Damp straw makes smoke.
烟会让孩子睡着，他们还巴不得呢
Smoke sends a boy to sleep, and that's what he wants.
小孩子都很懒的
Boys is very Iazy, gentlemen.
但一团火就能让他们上杆子跑出来 没有比这个更灵的了
But there's nothing Iike a good hot blaze to make them come out in a run.
而且很人道
It's humane too. Yes.
即使他们粘在烟囱上了
Because even if they've stuck in the chimney...
...脚板一热，他们就得赶紧下来
...roasting their feet makes them struggle to extricate theirselves.
是啊
Yes.
我想他喜欢扫烟囱这个活儿的吧？
I suppose he's fond of chimney sweeping?
没错，大人
He dotes on it, Your Worship.
好吧，那我就要签契约了...
Very well. I will sign the indentures...
...把他签给....
...to make him Mr....
甘菲尔先生做学徒
Mr. Gamfield's apprentice.
孩子
My boy.
孩子，你脸色苍白又惊慌失措
My boy, you Iook pale and alarmed.
出什么事了？
What's the matter?
求求您，先生，求求您，先生
PIease, sir. PIease, sir.
怎么了，孩子？
What is it, my boy?
- 别.... - 够了
-Don't.... -Now then.
别.... 别....
Don't.... Don't....
说吧，孩子，别什么？
Go on, my boy. Don't what?
求您别让这个可怕的人把我带走，先生
PIease don't send me away with this dreadful man, sir.
阴险狡猾的孤儿我见得多了....
Of all the designing orphans that I've ever seen....
- 闭嘴，执事 - 你是在跟我说话吗，大人？
-Hold your tongue, beadle. -Did Your Worship speak to me?
是的，闭嘴
Yes, hold your tongue.
不，不行
No. No, out of the question.
我拒绝签这张契约
We refuse to sanction these indentures.
把这孩子带走
Take the boy away.
好好待他
And treat him kindly.
看来他需要善待
He seems to want it.
我已经给昨晚去世的两位女士量好了尺寸
I've just taken the measure of the two women that died Iast night.
你要发财了，苏尔伯雷先生
You'II make your fortune, Mr. Sowerberry.
您这么认为吗？
Think so?
理事会出的价钱太少啦
The prices allowed by the board are very small.
棺材不也不大吗？
So are the coffins.
顺便问一下，你知不知道有谁想找个仆童？
By the by, you don't know anybody who wants a boy, do you?
报酬很可观，苏尔伯雷先生，很可观
Liberal terms, Mr. Sowerberry. Liberal terms.
现在你要见你的新师傅了...
Now, as you are to meet your new master...
...把帽子拉起来
...pull that cap off your eyes.
头抬起来，“先生”
Hold your head up, sir.
把眼睛擦干，“先生”
Dry your eyes, sir.
- 是你吗，邦布尔？ - 不会是别人，苏尔伯雷先生
-Is that you, Bumble? -No one else, Mr. Sowerberry.
我把那个孤儿带来了 奥利弗・忒斯特
I've brought the orphan, OIiver Twist.
那么说他是那个孤儿？
So this is the orphan, is it?
苏尔伯雷太太...
Mrs. Sowerberry...
...能不能请你过来一下，亲爱的？
...will you have the goodness to come here a moment, my dear?
奥利弗・忒斯特
OIiver Twist.
孤儿怎么会有名字？
How comes an orphan to have any name at all?
- 我给起的 - 你，邦布尔先生？
-I invented it. -You, Mr. Bumble?
我，苏尔伯雷先生
I, Mr. Sowerberry.
我按字母顺序给这些孤儿起名字
I name all our foundlings in alphabetical order.
最后一个是S
The Iast was S.
我给起了斯瓦布尔
Swubble, I named him.
这个是T，我给起了忒斯特
This was a T. Twist, I named him.
下一个是恩文...
Next one as comes will be Unwin...
...再下一个是维金斯
...and the next, Vilkins.
我把整个字母表的名字都准备好了 一直到Z
I've got names ready all through the alphabet, right up to Z.
哎呀，你可是个大文豪呢，先生
Why, you're quite a Iiterary character, sir.
嗯，嗯...
Well, well...
- ...没准就是呢 - 苏尔伯雷太太...
-...perhaps I may be. -Mrs. Sowerberry...
...这是救济院的孤儿
...this is the orphan from the workhouse.
天哪，他可真瘦小
Dear me, he's very small.
但他会长大的，苏尔伯雷太太 会长大的
But he'II grow, Mrs. Sowerberry. He'II grow.
是啊，在我这里吃的好喝得好 我敢说他肯定会的
Yes, I daresay he will. On our food and drink.
救济院的孩子吃得都比一般孩子多
Workhouse boys always cost more to keep than they're worth.
到楼下去，瘦皮猴
Get downstairs, you bag of bones.
夏洛特...
Here, Charlotte...
...把我们给狗准备的冷饭给这孩子
...give this boy some of the cold bits that were put by for the dog.
我猜你不会介意睡在棺材旁边
You don't mind sleeping among the coffins, I suppose.
你介意不介意都一样...
Well, it doesn't much matter whether you do or don't...
...没别的地方给你睡
...for you can't sleep anywhere else.
开门？
Open the door, will you?
- 你是新来的小子？ - 是的，先生
-You the new boy? -Yes, sir.
- 你多大了？ - 10岁，先生
-How old are you? -Ten, sir.
我进来后要好好教训你一顿，救济院的小子
Then I'II whop you one when I get in, you workhouse brat.
请问，先生 是您敲门的吗？
I beg your pardon, sir. Did you knock?
是我踢的
I kicked.
您要买棺材吗，先生？
Did you want a coffin, sir?
- 我猜你不知道我是谁 - 不知道，先生
-You don't know who I am, I suppose. -No, sir.
我是诺亚・克雷波尔先生 你归我管
Well, I'm Mr. Noah CIaypole. And you're under me.
现在把窗板关上
Now, take down the shutters.
我从师傅的早餐里给你留了点熏肉
Saved a nice Iittle bit of bacon for you from the master's breakfast.
到角落去吃，动作快点
In the corner with you. And be quick about it.
他们等你看铺子呢，听到了吗？
They'II want you to mind the shop. Do you hear?
没听到吗，救济院的？ 到角落里去
Do you hear, Workhouse? In the corner.
老天啊，诺亚，别管这孩子了
Oh, Lord, Noah, Iet the boy alone.
别管他？
Let him alone?
谁愿意管他了？
Why, everybody's Iet him alone.
他的爸爸，妈妈，所有的亲戚都不管他了
His mother, father and all his relations has Iet him alone.
所有他需要有人来管了
So he needs someone who don't.
晚餐
Supper.
奥利弗，你还没做完吗？
OIiver, ain't you done yet?
我还从来没见过这么没用的孩子 到楼下去
I've never known such an idle boy. Get down them stairs.
苏尔伯雷先生...
Mr. Sowerberry...
...进晚餐了
...supper.
- 我有个想法，亲爱的 - 想法？
-I've had a thought, my dear. -Had a thought?
那你要小心了，苏尔伯雷先生 你会得脑膜炎的
You want to be careful, Mr. Sowerberry, you'II get brain fever.
- 是关于小忒斯特的 - 他怎么了？
-It's about young Twist. -What about him?
- 一个很好看的孩子 - 当然啦，他吃得可不少
-A very good-Iooking boy. -He will be. He eats enough.
他脸上有一种忧伤的表情，亲爱的
There's an expression of melancholy in his face, my dear.
他能成为一个出色的送殡人，亲爱的
He would make a delightful mute, my Iove.
我-- 我不是说参加成人葬礼的 一般送殡人...
I-- I don't mean a regular mute to attend grown-up funerals, my dear...
...是儿童出殡的
...but only for children's practice.
看看他
Look at him.
救济院的小鬼头，看啊
A workhouse boy and a sneak. Look at him.
记住我的话，他会被绞死的
Mark my words, I'II see him hung.
不用多久
Can't be too soon.
救济院的，你妈妈呢？
Workhouse, how's your mother?
她死了
She's dead.
怎么死的？
What'd she die of, Workhouse?
你要哭了吗，救济院的？
You gonna cry, Workhouse?
- 什么事让你哭的？ - 不是你
-What set you off? -Not you.
- 不是我？ - 不是你
-Not me, eh? -No, not you.
你最好别说我妈妈的事
And you better not say anything about my mother.
最好？
Better not?
你妈妈的事？
About your mother?
我很抱歉，我很可怜你
Well, I'm very sorry, and I pity you very much.
但你必须知道，救济院的...
But you must know, Workhouse...
...你妈妈准不是个好东西
...your mother was a regular right-down bad one.
- 你说什么？ - 你妈妈不是个好东西
-What did you say? -A regular right-down bad one.
她死得正是时候...
It's a good thing she died when she did...
...不然的话，她准是在做苦工 或是被流放了
...or she'd be hard Iaboring or transported.
要么就是被绞死了，这个可能性最大 是吗，救济院的？
Or hung. Which is most Iikely, isn't it, Workhouse?
救命啊，夏洛特太太！
Help, Mrs. Charlotte!
他要杀了我了，救命啊！
He'II murder me. Help!
救命，走开！
Help. Get off!
老天啊，帮帮我！
For God's sake, help me!
太太，他要杀了我！
My missus, he's murdering me!
- 走开，走开！ - 把他拉开，夏洛特
-Get off. Get off me now! -Get him, Charlotte.
把他拉到外面去，快
Get him now. Go out with him. Come on.
- 救济院的魔鬼 - 我要教训教训你！
-Workhouse devil. -I'II Iearn you!
- 你这个小坏蛋！ - 把门打开，夏洛特
-You brat! -Get the door, Charlotte.
把他仍进去
In with him. In.
太凶残了，先生
Very violent indeed, sir.
太太说...
And the missus said...
...如果邦布尔先生能拨冗...
...if Mr. Bumble can spare the time...
...就可以来教训他了...
...then Mr. Bumble's to flog him...
...因为师傅出去了
...because the master's out.
- 在这里面 - 奥利弗？
-In there. -OIiver?
让我出去！
Let me out of here!
- 听到我说话吗，奥利弗？ - 听到了
-Do you know this here voice, OIiver? -Yes.
你不怕吗？
Ain't you afraid of it, sir?
听到我的说话，你不打颤吗？
Ain't you trembling while I speak, sir?
不！
No!
- 他准是疯了 - 不是疯了，是肉
-He must be mad. -It's not madness, ma'am, it's meat.
- 肉？ - 肉，太太，肉
-Meat? -Meat, ma'am, meat.
你给他吃得太多了
You've overfed him.
如果你一直给他喝粥的话 就不会有这种事情了
If you'd kept this boy on gruel, this would never have happened.
天哪，真是好心没好报
Dear, dear. This comes of being Iiberal.
到底是怎么回事情？
What's all this?
奥利弗・忒斯特突然发狂了 苏尔伯雷先生
OIiver Twist has turned violent, Mr. Sowerberry.
看他把我的眼睛打的，先生
Look what he's done to my eye, sir.
你呀，你呀！
Now then. Now then.
- 你是个好孩子，不是吗？ - 他侮辱我的妈妈
-You're a nice young fellow, ain't you? -He called my mother names.
要是他死了怎么办 你这个忘恩负义的家伙！
Well, and what if he did, you Iittle ungrateful wretch!
她活该，报应还不够呢
She deserved what he said and worse.
- 不是的！ - 是的！
-She didn't! -She did!
你说谎！
It's a Iie!
别干站着了，苏尔伯雷先生 他说我扯谎呢
Do something, Mr. Sowerberry. He called me a Iiar.
别干站着了！
Do something!
对不起，小姐...
I beg your pardon, miss...
...您能不能好心...？
...but would you be so kind--?
滚远点
Get off my Iand.
我不欢迎乞丐，滚！
I don't want no beggars here. Go on!
滚！ 要不我就放狗了！
Get off! Or I'II put the dog on you!
我没有多少，就这点也够救你的小命了
I haven't much, but you're more than welcome to it.
当心点，烫的
Be careful, it's hot.
一看到你我的心就一抽
Seeing you gave me such a turn.
我眼睛不好使了，但...
My eyes ain't what they were. But...
...我一时把你....
...I just thought for a moment....
你这么小，怎么一个人出门？
Why are you on the road at all, a Iittle mite Iike you?
- 你要去哪儿？ - 伦敦，夫人
-Where are you headed? -London, ma'am.
伦敦？
London?
伦敦
London.
哦，天哪，天哪
Dear, oh, dear, oh, dear.
你好，小哥
Hello, my man.
你这是怎么了？
And what's your game?
你不住附近吧？
You're not from these parts?
打哪儿来的？
Where you from, then?
我已经走了7天了
I've been walking. Seven days.
7天？啊！
Seven days? Cor.
我猜你想吃东西吧？
I expect you want grub?
保准你能吃到
And you shall have it.
我现在手头也有点紧...
I'm at a Iow-water mark meself just at the moment...
...但我会想办法的
...but I'II fork out and stump.
来吧，站起来
Come on, up with you, on your pins.
这些不会再出来了吧？
And these won't get out again?
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
哦，顺便说一下...
Oh, by the by...
...我叫杰克・道金斯 大家都叫我机灵鬼
...my name is Jack Dawkins, better known as the Artful Dodger.
奥利弗・忒斯特
OIiver Twist.
你为什么叫机灵鬼？
Why are you known as the Artful Dodger?
这就是原因
That's why.
有住的地方吗？
Got any Iodgings?
钱呢？
Money?
看来今晚你要找地方睡觉了，是吗？
I suppose you want someplace to sleep tonight, don't you?
蝾螈
Baby newt.
蝾螈，4便士一个
Buy a baby newt, 4 pennies.
你走这么远，不是铁嘴的命令吧
I expect you walking for so Iong was a beak's order.
- 铁嘴是什么？ - 你不知道铁嘴是什么？
-What does that mean? -Don't you know what a beak is?
- 是鸟嘴吗？ - 啊，你还真是个雏儿
-A bird's mouth, isn't it? -Cor, you are green.
铁嘴就是治安推事，你到底是哪儿人啊？
A beak's a magistrate, my son. Where you been all your Iife?
你给我滚开！
Get off me, you!
你自找的，活该
That's it, you asked for it.
回来啊，我有话对你说
Come back here. I wanna talk to you.
Lucky heather.
...我告诉你，伙计，我来的那个地方
--from where I am, mate, I'm telling you.
回家！
Go home!
放开！
Get off of that!
回家去！
Go back home!
- 喂 - 李子满贯（口令）
-Now then. -PIummy and slam.
- 有两个人，那个是谁？ - 新来的
-There's two of you. Who's he? -A new pal.
- 他打哪儿来？ - 没听说的地方
-Where'd he come from? -Greenland.
- 老头在吗？ - 在楼上，挑手帕呢
-Is the old one there? -Upstairs, sorting the wipes.
就是他，费金. 我的新朋友，奥利弗・忒斯特
This is him, Fagin. My new friend, OIiver Twist.
好啊，好啊，奥利弗・忒斯特
Well, well, OIiver Twist.
希望能有幸进一步跟你交朋友
I hope I have the honor of a more intimate acquaintance.
我们非常高兴见到你，奥利弗 非常
We're very glad to see you, OIiver. Very.
机灵鬼，把香肠拿下来...
Dodger, take off the sausages...
...给奥利弗腾个地方出来
...and Iet's make a space at the table for OIiver.
你看的是手帕，亲爱的？
You were staring at the pocket handkerchiefs, eh, my dear?
不少吧？
There's a good many of them, ain't there?
我们准备挑出来洗一洗
We've just Iooked them out, ready for the wash.
就这么回事，亲爱的
That's all, my dear.
吹一下
BIow it.
烫的，吹一下
Hot. BIow it.
奥利弗，你得喝一杯...
Now then, OIiver, what you must have...
...热杜松子酒加水，暖暖身子
...is a hot gin and water. Warms the cockles.
快点喝，另一位先生还等着用杯子呢
Only, drink it quick because another of these gentlemen wants the tumbler.
他是个好孩子
He's such a nice Iad.
我有种感觉，他会是把好手的
I have a feeling he'II turn out a hard worker.
是啊，是把好手
Yeah, a hard worker.
奥利弗？
OIiver?
聪明狗
CIever dogs.
聪明的小狗
好家伙
Fine fellows.
都是好家伙
AII fine fellows.
好家伙
Fine fellows.
你干吗监视我？ 你怎么会醒着的？
What do you watch me for? Why are you awake?
你看见什么了？ 说啊，孩子！
What have you seen? Speak out, boy!
快说，否则要你命！
Quick. Quick, or it's your Iife!
我再也睡不着了，先生
I wasn't able to sleep any Ionger, sir.
如果打扰了您，我非常抱歉
I'm very sorry if I disturbed you.
- 刚才你没醒吧？ - 没有，先生
-You were not awake a moment ago? -No, sir.
- 真的吗？ - 真的, 先生
-You sure? -Yes, sir.
你当然是睡着了，我知道的，宝贝儿
Of course you were asleep, my dear. I know that.
我只是想吓吓你
I only tried to frighten you.
你是个勇敢的孩子，奥利弗
You're a brave boy, OIiver.
你看见那些漂亮的玩意儿了吗，宝贝儿？
Did you see any of those pretty things, my dear?
看见了，先生
Yes, sir.
那些....
They....
那些都是我的，奥利弗 我的一点可怜的财产
They're mine, OIiver. My Iittle property.
是我养老用的
For my old age.
这是我们的小秘密
It's our secret.
- 明白了吗，宝贝儿？ - 明白了，先生
-You understand, my dear? -Yes, sir.
我现在可以起来了吗，先生？
Can I go up now, sir?
起来吧....
Now....
我希望你们早上没偷懒，宝贝们
I hope you've been at work this morning, my dears.
- 可卖力了 - 尽心尽力
-Hard. -As nails.
好孩子
Good boys.
- 给我看看，你有些什么，机灵鬼？ - 几个皮夹子
-What you got, Dodger? -Couple of pocketbooks.
- 高档吗？ - 还不错
-Lined? -Pretty well.
好啊
Yeah.
机灵鬼
Dodge.
我不知道，机灵鬼
I don't know, Dodge.
嗯...
Well...
...好像有点轻...
...not as heavy as they might be...
...但很干净...
...but very neat...
...做工也不错
...and nicely made.
真是个机灵鬼，是吗，奥利弗？
Ingenious workman, ain't he, OIiver?
是的，先生
Indeed, sir.
查理，你呢，宝贝儿？
And, Charley, what have you got, my dear?
- 小手巾儿 - 小手巾儿？
-Wipes. -Wipes?
货色不错
They're very good ones.
很不错
Very.
这个标记做得不好
You haven't marked them well.
得用针挑出来，我们--
The marks should be picked out with a needle. And we'II--
我们教奥利弗怎么做
We'II teach OIiver how to do it.
- 可以吗，奥利弗？ - 请吧，先生
-Shall us, OIiver? -If you please, sir.
你愿意跟查理・贝茨一样做手帕 是这样吗？
You'd Iike to make handkerchiefs as easy as Charley Bates, wouldn't you?
非常乐意，如果您教我的话，先生
Very much indeed, if you'II teach me, sir.
我还没见过这么嫩的雏儿
I've never met anyone so green.
好了，孩子们...
Now then, boys...
...开始吧
...the game.
我们教奥利弗...
We'II show OIiver...
...如何做手帕
...how to make pocket handkerchiefs.
你愿意玩游戏吗？
You'd Iike to play a game, wouldn't you?
是的，先生
Yes, sir.
- 几点了，老爹？ - 现在是...
-Got the time, guv? -It's...
...8点
...8:00.
- 在玩游戏吗，费金？ - 老一套了，亲爱的
-PIaying the game, were we, Fagin? -As is our custom, my dear.
- 他是新来的吧，叫什么？ - 他叫奥利弗
-He's new. Who's he? -Oh, this is OIiver.
奥利弗...
OIiver...
...这俩位是好朋友，贝特和南希
...these are our very good friends Bet and Nancy.
看见了吗，机灵鬼，你得好好跟他学学
See, Dodger, you wanna Iearn from him.
他多有礼貌啊，一位真正的绅士
He's got manners, he has. A proper gentleman.
外面太冷了，所以我们才进来
We popped in because we were that cold inside.
随时欢迎，亲爱的
As is your custom, my dear.
- 查理 - 来吧，奥利弗，坐这儿来
-Charley. -Come on, OIiver. Join us.
还是说你不愿意跟普通人坐一块儿？
Or don't you sit with the common folk?
你得多加小心，奥利弗
Now, you wanna be careful of this Iot, OIiver.
- 他们会教你... - 教他挑标记
-They'II have you picking-- -Picking out the marks.
我们教的就是这个，奥利弗，是吗？
Just what we was teaching him, ain't it, OIiver, my dear?
- 是的，先生 - “是的，先生”？
-Yes, sir. -"Yes, sir"?
你知道是对谁在说话吧？
You know who you're talking to, do you?
你到这儿来，你妈妈会怎么说？
What's your mother got to say about you being here?
我没有妈妈，我是孤儿
I haven't got a mother. I'm an orphan.
那你就来对地方了
You're in the right company, then.
来吧，奥利弗，我来教你怎么玩
Come on, OIiver, I'II teach you how to play.
这叫做“偷机”
It's called Spec or Speculation.
每人三张牌，他翻过来的那张...
Three cards each, and then the one he turns up...
...就是王牌
...is trumps.
这种日子是不是很快活啊，宝贝儿？
This is a pleasant Iife, ain't it, my dear?
- 我什么时候可以出去呢？ - 快了，快了
-When can I go out, sir? -Soon. Soon.
我们...
Let's--
来看看你都学会了什么
Let's see what you've Iearned.
- 喜欢吗？ - 喜欢，先生
-Would you Iike that? -Oh, yes, sir.
看你能不能在我不注意的情况下...
See if you can take this out...
...把它拿出来
...without my feeling it.
拿走了吗？
Is it gone?
你真是个聪明的孩子，宝贝儿
You're a clever boy, my dear.
我还没见过更聪明的
I never saw a sharper Iad.
这是一个先令，拿去吧
Here's a shilling for you.
跟机灵鬼还有查理学着点
Make the Dodger and Charley your models.
特别是机灵鬼，宝贝儿
Especially the Dodger, my dear.
他会是个大人物的，你也会
He'II be a great man himself, make you one too.
你就这么下去...
You go on this way...
...会成为了不起的大人物
...you'II be the greatest man of the time.
非常感谢，先生
Thank you very much, sir.
漂亮的苹果，来看看漂亮的苹果
Lovely white apples. Get your Iovely apples.
来啊，本市最大的卷心菜
Biggest cabbages in town. Come on.
你是说那个宽边的？
You mean that one with the wide rim?
太贵了
Too expensive.
小偷！ 你的手帕，先生
Thief! Your handkerchief, sir.
拦住他，小偷！
Stop, thief!
拦住他！
Stop!
小偷！
Thief!
- 你是个贼！ - 抓住他！
-You're a thief! -Get him!
- 抓住他！ - 抓住那个男孩！
-Stop him! -Stop that boy!
小偷！
Thief!
抓住他，小偷！
Stop, thief!
小偷！
Thief!
抓住他！
Stop him!
小心
Mind out.
抓住他！
Stop, thief!
那边，在那边
There, over there.
那边！
That way!
- 抓住他，小偷！ 抓住他！ - 小偷！
-Stop, thief! Stop! -Thief!
- 你叫什么？ - 让他透口气
-What's your name, boy? -Give him some air.
他吓死了
He's scared to death.
- 那位先生呢？ - 先生来了
-Where's the gentleman? -Here's the gentleman now.
- 是这个孩子吗？ - 恐怕是的
-Is this the boy, sir? -Yes, I'm afraid it is.
回答得真妙啊，“恐怕是的”
That's a good one. Did you hear him, "afraid it is"?
- 可怜的家伙，自己受伤了 - 是的，是我干的，先生
-Poor fellow's hurt himself. -Yeah, I did that, sir.
关节打到了他嘴上，可我拦下他了
Hurt me knuckle against his mouth. But I stopped him.
- 起来！ - 不是我，先生，不是我
-Get up! -It wasn't me, sir. It wasn't me.
当然不是，小偷都这么说
Of course it wasn't. It never is.
- 起来 - 别伤了他
-Now get up. -Don't hurt him.
不，先生，我不会的
Oh, no, sir, I won't hurt him.
这边，先生
This way, gentlemen.
- 下一个？ - 这是我的姓名和地址，先生
-What's next? -That is my name and address, sir.
警官，这家伙是谁？
Officer, who is this fellow?
- 我叫布朗罗 - 闭嘴
-My name is Brownlow. -Hold your tongue.
警官，这家伙犯了什么罪？
Officer, what's this fellow charged with?
哦，不，不是他，大人
Oh, no, no. He's not charged, Your Worship.
他是来指控这个孩子的
He appears against the boy.
- 让他发誓 - 在我发誓之前...
-Swear him. -Before I am sworn...
- ...我必须进上一言 - 闭嘴，先生
-...I must beg to say one word. -Hold your tongue, sir.
- 我不，先生！ - 即刻闭嘴
-I will not, sir! -Hold your tongue this instant.
你是个鲁莽无礼的家伙
You're an insolent, impertinent fellow.
- 你竟敢辱骂推事 - 什么？
-How dare you bully a magistrate. -What?
让他发誓，我不想听他废话了 让他发誓
Swear this person. I'II not hear another word. Swear him.
“我郑重发誓，所言皆为事实，上帝作证”
"I do solemnly swear to tell the whole truth, so help me God."
- 你指控这孩子什么？ - 我正在书店...
-What's the charge against the boy? -I was at a bookstore when--
闭嘴！警察呢？
Hold your tongue! Where's the policeman?
警官，怎么回事情？ 有证人吗？
Policeman, what is this? Are there any witnesses?
- 没有，大人 - 这孩子在生病
-None, Your Worship. -The boy is ill.
是的，恐怕如此
Oh, yes, I daresay.
过来，小乞丐，别在这里耍花样
Come along, you vagabond. None of your tricks here.
你叫什么？
What's your name?
你叫什么，你这个顽固的无赖？
What's your name, you hardened scoundrel?
- 警官，他叫什么名字？ - 你叫什么，孩子？
-Officer, what's his name? -What's your name, boy?
水，给我水
Some water. Some water.
他的名字叫萨姆・沃特斯，大人
He says his name is Sam Waters, Your Worship.
- 你住哪儿？ - 你住哪儿？
-Where does he Iive? -Where do you Iive?
- 没固定的地方，大人 - 废话
-Anywhere he can, Your Worship. -Stuff and nonsense.
别耍我
Don't try to make a fool out of me.
不，我想他真的是病了，大人
No, I think he really is ill, Your Worship.
我比你清楚，否则我就不姓方
I know better, or my name's not Fang.
站到旁边去，他在装死
Stand away, officer. He's shamming.
即席判决他劳役三个月
He stands committed for three months.
退庭
Hard Iabor, of course. CIear the office.
别，别！ 别带走他
Stop. Stop, stop! Don't take him away.
怎么回事？ 这人是谁？ 把他赶出去
What is this? Who is this? Turn this man out.
- 退庭 - 我不出去，我有话要说！
-CIear the office. -I will not be turned out! I will speak!
我都看见了，我是书店老板
I saw it all. I own the bookshop.
- 我要作证 - 你有什么要说的？
-I demand to be heard. -What have you got to say?
- 不是那个孩子 - 不是那个孩子？那是谁？
-It was not this boy. -Not this boy? Who was it, then?
在那位先生看书的时候 偷他东西的，是另外两个小孩
The robbery was committed by two others while the man was reading.
我看见了，看见这孩子都吓呆了
I saw it done. I saw that this boy was perfectly amazed by it.
你为什么不早来？
Why didn't you come before?
- 没人帮我看铺子 - 你说看书？
-I hadn't a soul to mind the shop. -Reading, you say?
那么说有书了
A book, I suppose.
是的，就攥在他手上呢
Yes, the very one he has in his hand.
天哪，我把这事给忘了
Oh, dear me, I forgot all about it.
好啊，你也是个好人啊
Well, you're a nice one.
指控无辜的孩子
To prefer a charge against an innocent boy.
我猜你是在一种极为可疑...
I consider, sir, that you've obtained that book...
...极不光彩的情况下取得这本书的
...under very suspicious and disreputable circumstances.
- 该死！ - 店主...
-Damn me! -Bookseller...
...你要指控他吗？
...do you want to press charges against him?
- 当然不 - 好吧...
-Certainly not. -Well...
...你是不是觉得挺幸运的...
...think yourself fortunate...
...书的主人拒绝指控你
...that the owner of the book declines to prosecute.
对这孩子的指控取消
The boy is discharged.
- 退庭 - 岂有此理
-CIear the office. -Damn me.
退庭！ 退庭！
CIear the office! CIear the office!
下一个案子
Next case.
来啊，走，先生 走起来，先生
Come on. Move along, sir, please. Just move along, sir.
真是位好心人，先生
There's a good gentleman, sir.
等等，哈里，我帮你一把
Hold on, Harry. I'II give you a hand.
小心脚下楼梯
Mind that step. Just mind that step there.
让一让路，先生
Make way for the Iaw, sir.
- 小心，小心点 - 他看上去年纪很小
-Careful. Careful with him. -He seems very young too.
帮我叫辆马车
Call a coach, pray.
- 好的，马上，先生 - 抱歉
-Yeah, right away, sir. -I'm sorry.
可怜的孩子
Poor boy.
- 小心，夫人 - 谢谢你，先生
-Mind yourself, madam. -Thank you, sir.
- 车来了，先生 - 谢谢，警官
-Got one, sir. -Thank you, officer.
我来吧，先生
Let me, sir.
好了
There we go.
- 能搭我一程吗，先生？ - 当然可以
-Will you drop me off, sir? -Of course.
好吧
AII right.
请帮忙抬一下他的头，先生
If you could just take his head, sir.
- 去哪儿？ - 本顿维尔
-Where to, sir? -Pentonville.
- 本顿维尔 - 是的
-Pentonville. -Yes.
回答我，他去哪儿了！？
Answer me! Where is he?
那孩子怎么样了？ 说啊，要不我掐死你！
What's become of the boy? Speak out, or I'II throttle you!
条子抓走了！ 放开我？！
The traps have got him! Let go of me, will you?!
大牛！
Bullseye!
谁扔的？谁往我头上扔的？
Who pitched this here at me? Who done it?
大牛，进来，你这鬼鬼祟祟的家伙
Bullseye. Come in, you sneaking warmint.
待在外面不进来干吗？
What you stopping outside for?
趴下
Lay down.
怎么了，费金？ 又虐待这些孩子了？
What you up to, Fagin? III-treating the boys again?
我奇怪他们怎么还没杀了你 如果换了是我，早动手了
A wonder they don't murder you. I would, if I was them.
别这么大声，你似乎不高兴，比尔
Don't speak so Ioud. You seem out of sorts, Bill.
给我杯喝的，小心别下毒药
Give us a drink. And mind you don't poison it.
查理
Charley.
好东西，比尔
Good stuff, Bill.
机灵鬼...
So, Dodger...
- ...这是唱的哪一出啊？ - 一个新来的孩子
-...what's it all about? -A new boy.
正在跟我们学徒
Come out with us afore he was rightly up to it.
- 被条子抓住了 - 你看，比尔...
-Got nabbed by the traps. -You see, Bill...
...我担心他说出一些 把我们也搭进去的事情
...I'm afraid he may say something which will get us into trouble.
你要被告发了，费金
You were blowed upon, Fagin.
也到时候了
And about time.
比尔，你看啊，如果我们完蛋了...
And I'm afraid, you see, Bill, that if the game was up with us...
...你的损失恐怕比我们大，亲爱的
...it would come out rather worse for you than it would for me, my dear.
那只能这么着了
There's only one thing for it.
得找人到局子里去看看 看看他怎么样了
Somebody's gotta find out at the office what's being done to him.
总得有人去
Somebody's gotta get hold of him somehow.
我才不愿意靠近警察局呢 为谁都不去
I ain't going near no police office. Not for nobody, nohow.
我有主意了，贝特会去的
I have it, the very thing. Bet will go.
- 是不是啊，亲爱的？ - 如果我去的话，会遭雷劈的
-Won't you, my dear? -I'm blessed if I will.
南希，亲爱的，你说呢？
Nancy, my dear, what do you say?
不行，你这套把戏行不通，费金
It won't do. There's no use in trying it on, Fagin.
- 你那是什么意思？ - 我说过了
-What do you mean by that? -What I say.
你是最合适的
Why, you're just the very person for it.
这儿没人认识你
Nobody about here knows anything about you.
我也不想让他们认识
And as I don't want them to neither.
我也不会同意的，比尔
It's rather more "no" than "yes" with me, Bill.
- 她会去的，费金 - 不，她不会，费金
-She'II go, Fagin. -No, she won't, Fagin.
她会去的，费金
Yes, she will, Fagin.
- 需要效劳吗，女士？ - 我在找我的弟弟
-Can I help you, miss? -I'm Iooking for my Iittle brother.
- 他是谁啊？ - 一个可爱的小男孩
-Now, who would he be? -A Iovely Iittle boy.
很文雅，很有礼貌
Lovely manners. Gentle as falling snow.
不在我们这里
We don't get many of those.
也许你该试试方先生的法庭
I think you'II be wanting Mr. Fang's court.
乔治，这位年轻女士要找她的弟弟
George, this here young Iady is Iooking for her brother.
那个昏倒，后来走掉的
The one that fainted and got away with it.
是啊，被一位先生带走了
Oh, yeah. Gentleman took him away.
什么先生？老天爷啊，什么先生？
What gentleman? Gracious heavens, what gentleman?
我想是住在本顿维尔
Well, Iives in Pentonville, I believe.
哦，老天
Oh, my God.
不，不，等等，等等
No, no. Wait, wait, wait.
他还有张名片在这里
His card's here somewhere.
给
Here we are.
谢谢，先生
Thank you, sir.
布朗罗先生
Mr. Brownlow.
他身上有种东西...
There's something in him...
...触动了我，贝德温太太
...that touched my heart, Mrs. Bedwin.
说不清楚
Can't explain it.
我也有这种感觉，先生
I feel the same, sir.
他是谁？干什么的？
Who is he? What is he?
你对他一无所知
You know nothing of him.
他发烧了，那又怎么了？
He had a fever. What of that?
坏人也会发烧的
Bad people have fevers sometimes.
我知道在牙买加有个家伙 因为谋杀主人而被绞死
I knew a man in Jamaica who was hanged for murdering his master.
他发过6次烧
He had a fever six times.
- 我知道他身上有善良的品质 - 你怎么知道的？
-I know there is goodness in him. -How do you know it?
善良和无辜
Goodness and innocence.
- 我第一眼看到他就知道了 - 他会骗人的
-I knew it the first moment I saw him. -He'II deceive you.
一有机会就会让你失望...
Let you down at the first opportunity...
...就像你以前做的那些善事一样
...Iike all your other good and innocent causes.
如果那孩子是善良无辜的 我就把自己的脑袋吃了，先生
If that boy's good and innocent, I'II eat my own head, sir.
感觉如果，亲爱的？
How do you feel, my dear?
很高兴，先生
Very happy, sir.
- 非常感谢您，先生 - 好孩子
-And very grateful to you indeed, sir. -Good boy.
有没有给他吃过东西了 贝德温？吃过流食了吗？
Have you given him any nourishment, Bedwin? Any slops?
不是流食，先生，是肉汤
Not slops, sir. Broth.
还有几杯葡萄酒...
A couple of glasses of port wine...
...对他的身体大有好处
...would have done him a great deal more good.
是吗，萨姆？
Wouldn't they, Sam?
我叫奥利弗，先生
My name is OIiver, sir.
奥利弗？
OIiver?
- 奥利弗什么？奥利弗・沃特斯？ - 不，先生，忒斯特，奥利弗・忒斯特
-OIiver what? OIiver Waters? -No, sir. Twist. OIiver Twist.
你为什么告诉推事，你叫沃特斯？
Why did you tell the magistrate your name was Waters?
我没这么告诉他，先生
I never told him so, sir.
- 你没有？ - 没有，先生
-You did not? -No, sir.
- 你不是在生我的气吧，先生？ - 不，没有
-You're not angry with me, are you? -No, no.
奇怪的名字
Queer name.
奥利弗・忒斯特
OIiver Twist.
这里的书很多吧，孩子？
There are a great many books, are there not, my boy?
是非常多，先生
A great number, sir.
从来没看过这么多
Never saw so many.
你想长大成为一个智者...
How would you Iike to grow up a clever man...
...撰写书籍吗？
...and write books?
我宁可读书，先生
I think I'd rather read them, sir.
为什么不想当作家呢？
Wouldn't you Iike to be a book writer?
我想做一个卖书的也许更好，先生
I think it'd be a better thing to be a bookseller, sir.
你说得真不错
You have said a very good thing.
好吧
Well, well.
我们不会把你培养成作家 只要学门正当的手艺就行
We won't make an author of you while there's an honest trade to be Iearned...
...或者去学制砖
...or brickmaking to turn to.
- 你是要赶我走吗，先生？ - 不，我亲爱的孩子
-Are you going to send me away, sir? -No, my dear child.
你不必担心我抛弃你...
You need not be afraid that I am going to desert you...
- ...除非你给我这么做的理由 - 不会的，永远都不会，先生
-...unless you give me cause. -I never, never will, sir.
希望如此...
I hope not...
...因为我非常愿意相信你 我为此也感到奇怪
...because I feel strongly disposed to trust you.
谢谢，先生
Thank you, sir.
我很高兴不用再穿这些了
I'm pleased I won't have to wear those again.
我们也很高兴，亲爱的
So are we all, my dear.
给
There.
您们好
Hello.
他是谁啊？
What's that?
这是小奥利弗・忒斯特
This is young OIiver Twist.
书店的伙计拿来一个包裹
The bookseller's boy brought a package.
哦，追上他，奥利弗 我还有些书要还回去
Oh, stop him, OIiver. There's some books to go back.
- 他就是那个得了感冒的孩子？ - 没错，就是
-Is that the boy who had the fever? -That's the boy.
当心点！
Mind out!
- 先生，没看到他 - 噢，真让人难过
-No sign of him, sir. -Oh, dear, I'm very sorry for that.
有几本书我很想今晚就还了
I particularly wished some books to be returned tonight.
为什么不让奥立弗去？ 让他去绝送对不会出问题
Why not send OIiver with them? He'II be sure to deliver them safely.
是的，您就交给我吧
Yes, do Iet me take them.
先生，如果你愿意的话，我可以跑过去
If you please, sir. I'II run all the way.
去吧，亲爱的
You shall go, my dear.
让贝德温太太告诉你怎么走
Ask Mrs. Bedwin to show you the way.
- 等等，奥立弗 - 是的，先生
-And, OIiver.... -Yes, sir?
把这个给书店老板
Give the bookseller this.
我欠他的钱
The money I owe him.
我马上回来,先生
I won't be Iong, sir.
- 你觉得这一去要多长时间？ - 你真觉得他会回来吗？
-How Iong do you think it'II take him? -You really expect him to come back?
- 你觉得不会？ - 带着5英镑？
-You don't? -With a ￡5 note in his pocket?
不，我不相信
No, I do not.
如果那个孩子回来的话...
If ever that boy returns to this house...
...我把自己的头吃掉，先生
...I'II eat my own head, sir.
还有你的头
And yours.
噢，弟弟！
Oh, my Iittle brother!
- 我没看错吧？ - 放开我，救命！
-I don't believe my eyes. -Let me go. Help!
- 上天有眼啊，我找到他了！ - 放开我！
-It's a miracle. Oh, I've found him. -PIease Iet me go.
- 噢，奥立弗，奥立弗 - 南希
-Oh, OIiver. OIiver. -Nancy.
你太调皮了，为了你我受了多少苦啊
You're such a naughty boy to make me suffer such distress on your account.
- 放开我！ - 小姐，这是怎么回事？
-Let go of me! -What's the matter, ma'am?
他离家出走了
He ran away from his parents.
- 放开我！ - 他们勤勤恳恳、受人敬重...
-Get off me! -Hard-working, respectable people...
...而他倒和一帮小贼和坏蛋混在一起
...and joined a set of thieves and bad characters.
他妈妈的心可伤透了
Broke his mother's heart.
- 可怜的孩子 - 回家吧，你这个小混蛋
Young wretch. Go home, you Iittle brute.
我没有爸妈！
I haven't got any parents.
我是孤儿！ 我住在本顿维尔
I'm an orphan. I Iive in Pentonville.
噢，别听他的，这也敢说啊
Oh, only hear him, how he braves it out.
- 什么？小奥立弗 - 是真的
-What? Young OIiver. -It's true.
回到你可怜的妈妈身边去！
You come home to your poor mother.
他们不能管我！我不认识他们！ 救命啊！救命！
I don't belong to them! I don't know them! Help! Help!
“救命，救命”？
"Help, help"?
我来救你的命，你个小混蛋！
I'II give you "help, help," you Iittle wretch!
这些书哪来的？
And these books.
是你偷来的？对吗？
Have you been a-stealing them, have you, eh?
- 你这个小混蛋 - 就是，你要好好教训他
-You Iittle villain. -That's right. You give it to him.
- 否则他还是不懂事 - 我会的，夫人
-Only way to bring him to his senses. -I will, missus.
跟我走，你这个小混蛋
And you come with me, you Iittle wretch.
这样对他有好处
It'II do him good.
- 这个男人是谁？救命啊！ - 大牛，看着他，好样的
-Who is this man? Help! -Bullseye, mind him, boy.
- 看着他 - 救命，救命！
-Mind him. -Help! Help!
你看看他，费金
Look at him, Fagin.
谁来扶我一下
Hold me, somebody.
谁来扶我一下，我要笑歪了
Hold me, somebody, while I Iaugh it out.
你看他穿的，费金
Look at his togs, Fagin.
很高兴看到你这么好，亲爱的
Delighted to see you Iooking so well, my dear.
为什么不提前写封信，说你要来啊？
Why didn't you write, my dear, and say you was coming?
那样我们就可以弄点热菜晚上吃了
We'd have got something warm for supper.
- 你好啊，费金，那是什么？ - 那是我的，费金
Hello, Fagin. What's that? That's mine, Fagin.
不不，亲爱的，那是我的，比尔，我的 那些书你拿去吧
Oh, no, my dear. Mine, Bill, mine. You shall have the books.
如果你不给我和南希，那我就把孩子带回去
If that ain't mine and Nancy's, I'II take the boy back again.
来吧，拿过来
Come on, hand over, will you?
这太不公平了吧，比尔 不公平啊，南希
This is hardly fair, Bill. Hardly fair, Nancy.
我才不管公不公平，给我拿过来
Fair or not fair, hand over, I tell you.
拿过来，你这个贪心的老骨头，拿来！
Give it here, you avaricious old skeleton. Give it here!
你给我们带来这么多麻烦 再拿这么多来都不够还！
That's for our share of the trouble, and not half enough neither.
如果你喜欢读书就留着吧，要么就卖掉
You may keep the books if you're fond of reading. If you ain't, sell them.
这些书真漂亮啊 字也很漂亮，是吗，奥立弗？
They're very pretty. Beautiful writing, isn't it, OIiver?
要送回去，这些书是布朗罗先生的！
Send them back. They belong to Mr. Brownlow.
这些书和钱都要送回去
Send them back. The books and the money.
他会以为是我偷了的
He'II think I stole them.
- 求你了，送回去吧 - 这孩子说的没错
-PIease send them back. -The boy's right.
没错，奥立弗，没错 他们会认为是你偷的
You're right, OIiver. You're right. They will think you've stolen them.
真是太好了，事情真是巧啊
It couldn't have happened better if we'd chosen our time.
救命啊，警察！
Help! Help! Police!
叫警察？让你叫！
Fetch the police! The police!
管住这条狗，比尔 孩子会被它咬成几块的
Keep back the dog, Bill. He'II tear the boy to pieces.
- 那是活该 - 救命！叫警察！
-Serve him right. -Help! Fetch the police!
叫警察！
Fetch the police!
走开，否则我把你的头劈成两半！
Step aside, or I'II split your head against the wall.
我不在乎
I don't care.
我不会让那条狗把孩子咬死 除非你先杀了我
That child shan't be torn down by the dog unless you kill me first.
大牛，来，大牛！
Bullseye. Here. Bullseye!
机灵鬼！
Dodger!
跟着他！
Get after him!
放开我！
Take your hands off me!
你想逃吗，亲爱的？
So you wanted to get away, my dear, did you?
想报警，对吗？
Wanted to call for the police, did you?
我们待会儿会好好治治你
We'II soon cure you of that.
我不能眼睁睁的看着你这样做，费金
I won't stand by and see this done, Fagin.
孩子你已经抓到了，你还想怎么样？
You got the boy. What more do you want?
别出声，南希 否则我会叫你以后都说不出话来
Keep quiet, Nancy, or I'II quieten you for a good Iong time to come.
就让他这样好了，随他去！
Let him be. Let him be!
你还真要做这孩子的好朋友啊
You're a fine one for the boy to make a friend of.
老天为证，我就是这样
God AImighty help me, I am.
他偷东西、撒谎、讨人厌，也就这样了
He's a thief, a Iiar, a devil, all that's bad from this night forth.
你这个老头还嫌打他不够吗？
Ain't that enough for the old wretch without blows?
好了，好了 我们讲话要文明点，文明点
Come, come, we must have civil words. Civil words.
文明？ 你跟我说文明？你这个老鬼！
Civil words? Civil words, you old villain!
我打小孩时起就帮你偷东西 还没有他一半岁数呢
I thieved for you when I was a child not half as old as this.
你总要活命吧
It's your Iiving.
没错，是你这个老鬼逼我这样的
Yes, and you're the wretch that drove me to it...
让我走上这条路 日日夜夜，直到死为止！
...and who will keep me at it, day and night, till I die!
机灵鬼，查理，让奥立弗去睡吧
Dodger, Charley, put OIiver to bed.
最好把那些衣服脱掉 穿这么好去睡觉太不像话了
Best to take them clothes off. They're too good to sleep in.
查理说得对 这套衣服要4个半便士呢
Charley's right. This here suit cost more than 4 pence ha'penny.
我从来没摸过这么舒服的料子 你呢，机灵鬼？
I never felt such Iovely stuff. Have you, Dodger?
我没穿过，不过我敢打赌...
Not me. But I'm willing to Iay odds...
...女王穿的衣服就是用这个料子的
...this is the same stuff the queen wears on Sundays.
快，抓住他
Quick, get him.
脱掉
Take it off.
把他抬起来
Lift him up.
好了
Up he goes.
脱鞋子
Get them shoes off.
吃点午饭吧，亲爱的？
Little something for your Iuncheon, my dear?
我们聊一会，好吗？
Shall we have a Iittle chat?
奥立弗？
OIiver?
好不好？
Shall us?
我觉得你这么久没听过人说话...
I expect you'd welcome...
...应该会喜欢听到才对啊 对吗，亲爱的？
...the sound of a human voice again, eh, my dear?
你知不知道...
Do you know...
...我觉得世上最大的罪过是什么，亲爱的？
...what I consider the greatest sin in the world, my dear?
忘恩负义
Ingratitude.
也就是你所犯的罪过...
And that's what you're guilty of...
...忘恩负义
...ingratitude.
我们带你回来，爱你 要不是我们，你早就饿死了
We took you in, we cherished you. If we hadn't, you'd have died of hunger.
你怎么报答我们呢？ 你逃跑了…
How do you repay us? You run away...
...还跑去叫警察 你让我们担心，还花费了不少
...you cry out for the police, you cause us great anxiety and expense.
过去也有个小家伙，很像你 我对他就像他爸爸一样好
There was a Iad once, just Iike you, and I was a father to him.
可是他和你一样，也逃跑了 他确实找到了警察
He ran away, Iike you. He indeed went to the police.
你知道他落得什么下场吗？
And can you guess how he ended up?
他被吊死了...
They hanged him...
...就在老城法庭
...at the OId Bailey.
我们提供了一些证据，虽然不全是真的...
Certain evidence was made available, not all of it precisely true...
...但足以保证我自己...
...but all of it necessary to provide for my own safety...
...和我朋友的安全
...and that of my friends.
就是这样，可怜的孩子
Yeah. Poor boy.
被吊死了
Hanged.
绞刑很吓人的，奥立弗
It's a terrible thing, hanging, OIiver.
天刚亮，在绞刑架上...
Dawn, the gallows...
...有绳子、有套索
...the rope, the noose.
你不一定要有罪，对吧，奥立弗
You don't always have to be guilty, you see, OIiver.
这年头他们要吊死你可不讲什么道理
They hang you for anything these days.
因为他们很喜欢吊人
That's because they're so very fond of hanging.
但是如果你按我说的做...
But if you do as you're told...
...我们还会是好朋友的
...we'II be very good friends yet.
奥立弗，你可以到处走走了
You must feel free to walk about now, OIiver.
没错，随便哪里
Yes, feel free.
- 来这里，奥立弗 - 什么事？
-Here, OIiver. -Yes?
你马上过来，为我打扮打扮
I'd Iike you to assist me in my toilet straightaway.
- 可以帮一下忙吗，小伙子？ - 没问题，我我希望有人陪陪
-Will you do that for me, my man? -AII right. I'II be glad to have company.
这才是好小子嘛 来，先为我脚套上光
There's a good fellow. You may start by japanning my trotter-cases.
简单点说，就是帮我擦擦鞋
In plain English, clean my boots.
真可惜，他不是个三只手
What a pity he ain't a prig.
他不知道什么才是好的
He don't know what's good for him.
我看你不知道什么是三只手吧？
I suppose you don't know what a prig is.
我知道的，三只手是....
Yes, I do. It's a....
就是贼
It's a thief.
你就是三只手，对吗？
You're one, aren't you?
对，我是，我们都是 连那条狗都是...
Yes, I am. And so we all are. Down to the dog...
...那狗摸起来舒服到家了
...and he's the downiest one of the Iot.
它也从来不会告密
And the Ieast given to peaching.
最多只会在证人席上吠两下...
He wouldn't so much as bark in a witness box...
- ...也不敢说主人坏话 - 它可是地地道道的基督教徒呢
-...for fear of committing himself. -He's an out-and-out Christian, he is.
你为什么要跟着费金，奥立弗？
Why don't you put yourself under Fagin, OIiver?
否则你会立即发大财的
You'II make a fortune out of hand.
像本顿维尔的老先生家，就是那个大房子
Like your old gentleman in Pentonville. Big house, that.
我偷偷看过里面，很漂亮嘛，对吧？
I had a peep at it, I did. Nice inside, was it?
是的，我还睡过真正的床，有自己的房间
Yes. And I slept in a proper bed. In my own room.
- 墙上的东西也不错，对吧？ - 确实是
-Good stuff on the walls, eh? -Yes. Indeed.
根在费金后面...
Put yourself under Fagin...
...你就没有那样的好房子啦
...and you'II be able to retire to a property just Iike that.
也不能像以前那么风光了
And do the genteel.
不，他害怕，怕挨绳圈子
No, he's scared he'II come to be scragged.
我不知道你说什么
I don't know what that means.
如果你不拿手帕和手表，诺利...
If you don't take pocket handkerchiefs and watches, Nolly...
...还有别的家伙会去拿 你会做的，别人也会做
...some other cove will. You have the same right to them as they have.
当然啦，当然啦
To be sure. To be sure.
道理很简单，亲爱的，很简单
It all Iies in a nutshell, my dear, in a nutshell.
要相信机灵鬼的话
Take the Dodger's word for it.
他可是相当懂行的
He understands the catechism of his trade.
车夫？
Cabby?
- 我从比尔哪儿来 - 为什么？
-I've come from Bill. -For what?
- 反正不是坏事 - 我不信
-For no harm. -I don't believe it.
我要是能帮你的话早就帮了，就是没能力
If I could help you, I would, but I've not the power.
我答应过他要让你乖点，安静点
Now, I've promised him you'II be good and silent.
否则，你只会给自己添麻烦
If you're not, you'II only do yourself harm.
还给我添麻烦
And me too.
他没闹吧？
Did he come quiet?
像只小羊羔一样乖
Like a Iamb.
坐下
Sit down.
我来给你上一课
And Iet me read you a Iecture.
你知道这是什么吗？
You know what this is?
- 知道 - 好的
-Yes. -Well, then.
这是火药
This is powder.
这是子弹
That here's a bullet.
这是从旧帽子上取下的一小块...
And this is a Iittle bit of an old hat...
...用来做弹塞
...for wadding.
- 这样就上好膛了 - 是的，我看到了，先生
-Now it's Ioaded. -Yes, I can see it is, sir.
我们出去的时候，除非我要跟你讲话...
If you speak a word when you're out of doors with me...
...如果你敢自己说一句话...
...unless I speak to you...
...这颗子弹就立马钻进你脑袋里
...this Ioading will go in your head without notice.
就是说，如果你决定擅自开口说话...
So if you do make up your mind to speak without Ieave...
...那就先把祷告做了吧
...says your prayers first.
让我明说了吧，你就是想说 要是让他搞砸了...
The short and Iong of what you mean is that if you're crossed by him...
...你就会让他脑袋吃一颗子弹...
...you'II prevent him from telling tales after...
...不让他把事情抖出去
...by shooting him through the head.
这样你就碰上好运气，不用被吊死了
And you'II take your chance of swinging for it.
没错，女人总是三两句话就能把事情说清楚
That's it. Women always put things in the fewest words.
晚饭，南希
Supper, Nancy.
动手前打会盹儿
And then a snooze afore starting.
好哥们，比尔
My pal Bill.
门没关，进来吧
The door's open, come in.
别嚷那么大声！
Don't make such a row.
点盏灯，托比
Show us a glim, Toby.
巴尼，点灯，带这位先生进来
Barney, a glim. Show the gentleman in.
巴尼？起来啊，帮帮忙
Barney? Wake up first, if convenient.
塞克斯先生，请进，请进
Mr. Sykes. Come in, sir, come in.
比尔，老兄，很高兴看到你
Bill, my boy. GIad to see you.
这是...？
Who's...?
- 这是谁？ - 就是那个孩子
-Who's this? -Only the boy.
- 费金先生的徒弟？ - 没错，时候到了
-One of Mr. Fagin's Iads? -Yeah. It's time.
没错
Right.
拿炮筒子来，巴尼
Barkers for me, Barney.
- 上了膛的 - 好的
-They're Ioaded. -Good.
- 你的家伙呢？ - 拿好了
-The persuaders? -Got them.
钥匙、钻头
Keys, center bits.
黑皮灯
Darkies.
没漏掉什么吧？
Nothing forgotten?
好了，没声音了
Yeah, it's all quiet.
不行的，不行的
I can't. I can't.
你得去
You will.
是布朗罗先生的房子
It's Mr. Brownlow's house.
求你了，别让我头他家的东西
Have mercy. Don't make me steal from him.
- 求求你了 - 来这儿
-Have mercy on me. -Come here.
看在上帝的份上，让我跑掉，死在田里算了
For God's sake, Iet me run away and die in the fields.
- 我再也不到伦敦来了 - 闭嘴
-I'II never come near London, never. -Shut it.
站起来，否则我让你脑浆溅到草地上去
Get up. Or I'II strew your brains on the grass.
我把你放进去
I'm putting you through there.
你到前门去，把门开了
Go to the front door and unfasten it.
不行，上面有门闩，我知道我够不着
I can't, there's a bolt at the top. I know it, I can't reach it.
- 那就找张椅子什么的站上去 - 去啊
-Well, stand on a chair or something. -Just do it.
往前门去 往前门走啊，混帐
To the door. To the front door, damn you.
谁啊？
Who's there?
贝德温太太？是你吗？
Mrs. Bedwin? Is that you?
过来，过来
Come here. Come here.
救我！救我！看在上帝的份上，救我！
Save me! Save me! Save me, for God's sake!
救命
Help!
救命！警察！
Help! Police!
抬上来
Give him here.
该死的，他流了这么多血
Oh, damnation, how he bleeds.
- 他伤得重吗？ - 应该让他伤得更重些
-Is he hit bad? -He's gotta be hit worse.
- 把手枪给我 - 什么？
-Give me a pistol. -What?
我们得灭了他，免得他通风报信
We gotta get rid of him, or he'II squeal.
我们得干掉他
We gotta do him in.
这，就在河边这
Here, here. Down here by the river.
但是，比尔！比尔！
But, Bill! Bill!
- 比尔？ - 救命啊！
-Bill? -Help!
救命！救命！
Help! Help!
- 比尔 - 救命！
-Bill. -Help!
拍
Snap.
好吗？
Well, well.
你好吗，老费？
How are you, Fagey?
走开，你们走开！比尔呢？
Scarce. Scarce! Where's Bill?
- 他在流血 - 发生什么事了？
-He's-- He's bleeding. -What happened?
我会马上告诉你
AII in good time.
不过我没吃饱喝足是不会谈正事的
I can't talk business till I've ate and drank.
南希，我说过了，走开，走开！
Nancy, I said, scarce. Scarce!
比尔哪去了？
Where's Bill?
赶快弄点吃的去，劳你大驾
Well, produce the sustenance, if you please.
机灵鬼！
Dodger!
南希，走开！
Nancy, scarce!
- 计划泡汤了 - 我也猜到了
-The crack failed. -I smelt that.
我最后问这一次，比尔哪里去了？
For the Iast time of asking, where's Bill?
机灵鬼
Dodger.
扶他上床，给他喝口酒
Put him to bed, give him a nip of gin.
这小子差点就害死我们啦，老费
The boy was about to blow on us, Fagey.
- 他被发现了 - 发现了？
-He was seen. -Seen?
他被发现了？谁发现他了？
He was seen? Who saw him?
两个老东西，他喊出声来了
Two old ones. He shouted out.
比尔傻掉了，开了枪
Bill Iost his head, fired his pistol....
- 打中了这孩子？ - 不知道，当时开了两枪
-And hit the boy? -I don't know. There was two shots.
比尔只开了一枪
Only one was Bill's.
我们只好逃命，我抱住这孩子，比尔跌倒了
We made a run for it. I had ahold of the boy, and Bill fell.
跌倒了？他有没有受伤？
Fell? Was he hurt?
没有，后来他是游回伦敦的呢
No. Last seen, he was swimming to London.
大牛
Bullseye.
我跟你说过的，不要带任何人进来
I told you not to bring a soul here.
你现在倒把这个魔鬼带来了
Now you've brought the devil.
你叫我带他来的
You said to fetch him.
他脑子烧过了头，什么都记不得了
His fever is that high, he don't remember nothing.
你很不舒服，对吗，比尔? 今天身体怎么样啊？
You're not well, are you, Bill? How do you feel today?
我身子虚得很呢
I'm as weak as water.
给我们来点喝的
Get us a drink.
- 什么破风把你吹到这里来了？ - 不是什么破风，亲爱的
-What evil wind has blowed you here? -No evil wind, my dear.
是你，比尔，是你说要和我讲话的
You, Bill, you. You said we need to speak.
你对那孩子做了什么？他在哪里？
What you done with that boy? Where is he?
他好得很，机灵鬼在看着他
Safe and sound. The Dodger's minding him.
他们现在形影不离呢
They're as close as Cain and Abel.
那孩子怎么啦，比尔？
What about the boy, Bill?
我们不想有谁告发我们，对吗？
We don't want anyone peaching on us, do we?
只要那孩子还活着，我们就是被吊死的命
And as Iong as that boy's alive, we're as good as hung.
那应该怎么办？
So, what's to be done?
- 不要动手 - 不动手？
-Nothing. -Nothing?
- 我还没好就不要动手 - 然后呢？
-Not till I'm better. -Then what?
- 然后我就了结了他 - 怎么了结啊，在哪呢？
-Then I'II do for him. -How, Bill? Where?
到伦敦郊外找条河把他淹死掉
Outside of London somewhere. I'II find a river and I'II drown him.
那孩子现在身子很弱，比尔，他受伤了
The boy's weak. Bill, he was wounded.
他连站都站不稳，就不要说走路了
He can hardly stand, Iet alone walk.
他什么时候走得动了就告诉我，我去带他走
When he can walk, tell me. I'II fetch him.
你走吧
Now, get out of here.
好
Yes.
好的
比尔，你说得没错
Bill, you're right.
我是出于好意啊
It's for the best.
我浑身烧得利害
I'm burning up.
给我吃点药吧，我的药呢？
Give me me physic. Where's me physic?
你怎么魂不守舍的？
You Iook Iike a corpse come back to Iife again.
- 发生了什么事？ - 没事
-What's the matter? -Nothing.
你干吗这么狠地瞪着我？
What do you Iook at me so hard for?
- 你在想什么？ - 想很多，比尔
-What you thinking of? -Of many things, Bill.
- 问这个干嘛？ - 我来告诉你吧
-What odds in that? -I'II tell you what it is.
你要不是害了感冒...
If you haven't caught the fever...
...就是有些不寻常的事情发生了
...then there's something more than usual in the wind.
或者是很危险的事
And something dangerous too.
把药给我，我说
Give me me physic, I say.
不，不，不
No, no, no.
没有见过这么犟的女人...
There ain't a stauncher-hearted girl going...
...早知道就把她的脖子给割了
...or I'd have cut her throat three months ago.
她可能是发烧了吧，就是的
She's got a fever coming on. That's it.
来，喝了会好些
Here. Make you feel better.
坐到这来
Sit aside me.
拿出你平时的样子来，否则我给你变个样 让你自己都认不出来
Put on your own face, or I'II alter it so you won't know it again.
- 等一下 - 好的，小姐
-Wait. -Ma'am.
- 你好？ - 布朗罗先生是不是住在这里？
-Yes? -Does Mr. Brownlow Iive here?
你是谁？你想干什么？你回去吧
Who are you? What do you want? Go around the back.
我想说说奥立弗・忒斯特的事
I have information about OIiver Twist.
他还好吗？他没有危险吧？
Is he all right? Is he safe?
- 他在哪？ - 我只跟布朗罗先生说
-Where is he? -I will only talk to Mr. Brownlow.
他不在
He's not here.
告诉他，那孩子是无辜的
The boy's innocent, tell him that.
- 他在哪里？ - 他很安全
-Where is he? -Safe.
- 但是不会一直都那样 - 他在哪里？
-But he may not be for Iong. -Where is he?
替我给布朗罗先生留个口信
Give Mr. Brownlow a message.
让他星期天凌晨...
Tell him to meet me on Sunday at midnight...
- ...到伦敦桥和我碰面 - 凌晨？
-...on London Bridge. -Midnight?
如果我不在的话...
And if I'm not there...
... 告诉他第二天，第三天晚上再去 我会在的，要告诉他
...then tell him to come the next night and the next. I'II be there. Tell him.
看啊，亲爱的 你就像从来没有受过伤一样
There, my dear, you Iook as good as new.
- 你感觉怎样？ - 累，先生
-How do you feel? -Tired, sir.
哦，当然，当然
Well, yes, yes.
早就过12点了 待会儿你就可以美美得睡一觉了
It is Iong after midnight. Shortly, you'II sleep a good sleep.
可是，我的意思是...
But my meaning was...
...你身子感觉怎样，奥立弗？
...how do you feel in yourself, OIiver?
好些了，谢谢你，先生
Better. Thank you, sir.
- 就是手臂还痛 - 过来坐
-But for the ache in my arm. -Come sit.
我有好东西可以对付它，亲爱的
I have the very thing for such pains as yours, my dear.
解开绷带
Undo the bandage.
噢，天啊
Oh, my God.
伤得不轻啊
It's a nasty wound.
我的妙方会治好它的 看着吧，亲爱的
But my magic will do the trick. You'II see, my dear.
这种药...
This remedy...
...是祖传秘方，没错...
...is older than time. Yes...
...亲爱的，是祖传秘方
...my dear, older than time.
父亲传给儿子...
It was handed down from father to son...
...父亲传给儿子，来自什么地方？
...father to son, and comes from...
没有谁知道
...who can say where?
谢谢你，先生，谢谢
Thank you, sir. Thank you.
谢谢你的好意，我永远不会忘记的
For your kindness. I'II always remember it.
这个...
Well....
永远不会
AIways.
没错，永远不会，亲爱的
Yes, always, my dear.
谁知道那会有多久啊
But who knows how Iong that will be.
离凌晨还有一个钟头
An hour this side of midnight.
这天还很阴沉
Dark and heavy it is too.
到此为止吧，晚安了
Good night for business, this.
真可惜，比尔，亲爱的 我们还没成功过一次呢
What a pity, Bill, my dear, there's none quite ready to be done.
对啊，这回你说对了
Yeah, for once, you're right.
那孩子什么时候才能好起来，走那一段路呢？
When will the boy be well enough to go on his travels?
- 我说过了，一两天就可以了 - 真可惜
-Like I say, Bill. In a day or two. -It's a pity.
- 我也有这种感觉 - 听你这么说我就放心了
-For I'm in the humor to. -Does me good to hear you.
今晚你像你自己了，比尔 这样才像你自己嘛
You're Iike yourself tonight, Bill. Quite Iike yourself.
你把这皱巴巴的爪子放在我肩上 我才不像自己呢...
I don't feel Iike myself when you Iay that withered claw on my shoulder...
...给我松开
...so take it away.
你好，南希
Hello, Nance.
这女孩这么晚到哪里去？
Where's the girl going to this time of night?
- 不远 - 这是什么话？
-Not far. -What answer's that?
- 你到哪里去？ - 我说了，不远
-Where you going? -I say, not far.
- 我问的是哪里？ - 我不知道哪里
-And I say, where? -I don't know where.
那我知道，哪儿都不要去，坐下
Then I do, nowhere. Sit down.
- 我不舒服，我想透透气 - 把脑袋伸到窗外去
-I'm not well. I want a breath of air. -Put your head out the window.
那还不够，我想到街上去
There's not enough there. I want it in the street.
那你就哪都不要去
Then you won't have it.
现在给我乖乖地呆在这里，行吗？
There. Now, stop quietly where you are, will you?
你知道你在干什么吗？
Do you know what you're doing?
我在干什么？
Do I know what I'm--?
我看你这个女人是疯掉了 敢这样对我说话？
I think this girl's Iost her senses. You talking to me in that way?
你要把我逼上绝路了
You'II drive me on to something desperate.
让我走，行吗？就现在，就这次
Now, Iet me go, will you? This minute, this instant.
- 休想！ - 叫他让我走，费金
-No! -Tell him to Iet me go, Fagin.
这样是为他好，你听见了吗？
It'II be better for him. Do you hear me?
好，我听见了
Aye, I hear you.
如果再过半分钟我还听见你嚷嚷...
And if I have to Iisten to you for half a minute Ionger...
...那只狗就会让你出不了声！
...the dog will tear some of that screaming voice out!
你是怎么啦，你个贱货，怎么回事？
What's come over you, you jade? What is it?
比尔，让我走吧
Bill, Iet me go.
让我走吧，你不知道自己在干什么
Let me go. You don't know what you're doing.
就去一个小时
For only one hour.
这娘们要是还没疯到头 我就把我的手脚一只一只砍下来
Cut my Iimbs off one by one if I don't think the girl's stark raving mad.
- 起来，给我起来！ - 不！
-Get up. Get up! -No.
给我呆在里面！
Now, stay there!
这个小娘们真够奇怪
What a precious, strange girl that is.
你说的没错，比尔，没错
You may say that, Bill, you may say that.
大晚上的她为什么要出去呢？
Why did she take it in her head to go out tonight?
固执，我看她很固执，亲爱的
Obstinacy. Women's obstinacy, I suppose, my dear.
我还以为我把她驯乖了 可她还是那个样儿
I thought I tamed her of that. But she's as bad as ever.
我看她是染上我的热病了，还没好呢
I think she's got a touch of my fever in her blood and it won't come out.
还真像
Like enough.
如果她再敢那样做，我就给他放放血
Well, if she's taken that way again, I'II Iet her a Iittle blood.
就用不着看医生了
Without troubling the doctor.
现在她又变了个花样
Why, now she's on the other tack.
晚安了
Good night.
过两天来找那个孩子把
In two days, Bill, come for the boy.
点灯送客
Light him down.
他要是摔倒了没人见着，多可怜啊
It's a pity he should fall and break his neck without anyone seeing it.
给他点盏灯
Show him a Iight.
怎么啦，亲爱的南希，这样闹腾是为什么？
What is it, Nancy dear, the reason for all this?
- 你说什么？ - 刚才的事
-What do you mean? -That matter just now.
我不会告诉别人
We'II speak of this anon.
我们俩算是朋友吧，南希
You have a friend in me, Nance.
老朋友，你早就认识我了，南希
A staunch friend. You know me of old, Nance.
我很了解你，晚安
I know you well. Good night.
机灵鬼...
Dodge...
...抽一口
...pull it in.
我的杯子已经满了，你没看到吗？
My glass is full already, can't you see?
麻烦来啦
Trouble?
机灵鬼
Dodger.
- 有没有老汤姆酒啊？ - 在十钟酒吧呢
-Let's find out where old Tom is, eh? -He's in the Ten Bells.
我们俩去弄点回家吧？
Shall we both take him home?
老实说...
Honestly...
...我没见着她
...I haven't seen her.
什么事？
Something up?
我....
I....
我想你帮我一个忙 帮这个忙要很小心，很注意
I want you to do a piece of work for me that requires great care and caution.
什么事？不要叫我去警局附近办事
What is it? I ain't going near no police office.
- 那不适合我去 - 办这件事一点危险也没有
-That don't suit me, that don't. -There's not the smallest danger in it.
一点都没有，我想你跟跟一个人
Not the smallest. I want someone dodged.
- 谁？一个老头？ - 年轻人
-Who, an old one? -Young one.
- 是谁？ - 我们的人
-Who is she? -One of us.
谁呀？
Who?
南希？
Nancy?
- 她最近怎么啦？ - 我也不清楚她在干什么...
-What's she been up to? -Not sure she's been up to anything...
...亲爱的，所以我才叫你跟她啊
...my dear, that's why I want her dodged.
她可能想跟人说我们的事，她不能说的
She may want to talk to people she shouldn't want to talk to.
我想知道她去了哪里，见了谁，说了什么
I want to know where she goes, who she sees, what she says.
南希
Nancy.
我不知道，她是个好人，南希啊
I don't know. She's a good one, is Nancy.
给你一个英镑，亲爱的，实打实一个英镑
A pound, my dear. One whole pound.
布朗罗先生？
Mr. Brownlow?
是的
Yes.
我不敢在这里说，这边走，跟我来
I'm afraid to speak to you here. Come away. Follow me.
已经够远了
This is far enough.
- 为什么不在这上面说？ - 我说过了，我害怕
-Why can't we speak up there? -I told you, I'm afraid.
可能有人跟踪我
I may be followed.
我到这儿来是因为...
I'm here because you told...
...你告诉我的管家 说你有奥立弗・忒斯特的消息
...my housekeeper you have information concerning OIiver Twist.
- 没错 - 告诉我吧
-So I have. -Tell me.
她在一个恶棍手中...
He's being held by the devil...
...很快要被送到另外一个恶人手上，他想....
...and he's handing him over to another what means to....
告诉我多一些，他是不是你身边的人？
I must know more. Is it someone close to you?
- 一个是，一个不是 - 不管这两个人是谁...
-One is. One ain't. -These men, whoever they are...
- ...你都要说出来 - 我不会的
-...must be delivered up by you. -Never.
他干尽坏事，我也没什么两样 我不会出卖他的
Bad a Iife as he has Ied, I've Ied a bad Iife too, and I will not turn upon him.
另外一个
The other.
- 费金，孩子在他手上 - 费金
-Fagin. He has the boy. -Fagin.
你要能找到费金，就找到那小孩了
Find Fagin, you'II find the boy.
- 他在哪里？ - 斯皮达菲
-Where is he? -Spitalfields.
我不能再说了，已经说太多了
That's all I'II say. I've said too much.
不要让别人知道是我告诉你的
No one must never know who told you.
- 答应我 - 我答应你
-Promise. -I promise.
- 明天我就去警察局 - 不，今晚就要去
-Tomorrow I'II go to the police. -No, you must do it tonight.
说费金的名字，那些条子就会知道了
Just say Fagin, and the traps will know.
- 条子？ - 警察
-The traps? -The police.
- 你要什么作为酬劳？ - 什么都不要
-What can I do to serve you? -Nothing.
你帮不了我，我已经完全失望了
You can do nothing. I am past all hope indeed.
把这个收下吧
Take this as a reward.
不，我来这里不是为了钱
No, I've not done this for money.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
晚安，晚安
Good night. Good night.
千万不要说是谁告诉你的
Never-- Never say who told you.
你看他
Look at him.
多可惜啊，看他那小脸蛋...
What a shame it is. With his face...
...他可以在教堂掏老太太的口袋
...he could pick old Iadies' pockets in church.
这小脸蛋能帮我们发财呢
His face could be a fortune to us.
你改变主意了？
You changing your mind?
没有
No.
不，比尔，必须要那样做
No, Bill, it has to be done.
费金！费金
Fagin! Fagin.
- 你怎么啦，机灵鬼？ - 我得和费金单独说
-What's got into you, Dodger? -I have to see Fagin alone.
不不，在比尔面前说没关系
No, no, you can speak in front of Bill.
- 不，不行 - 可以的，说啊，机灵鬼，说吧
-No, I can't. -Yes, you can. Speak, Dodger, tell us.
- 是南希 - 南希怎么啦？
-Nancy. -What about Nancy?
他帮了我一个小忙，比尔 我让他跟踪了南希
He done a bit of work for me, Bill. I had him dodge Nancy.
你说什么？
What do you mean?
告诉我们，机灵鬼，你跟踪了她？
Tell us, Dodger. You followed her?
是的，到了伦敦桥
Yes. To London Bridge.
然后呢？在伦敦桥上干什么了？
And what? What on London Bridge?
她和一个老东西见了面，是个老先生
She met an old one. A gentleman.
- 然后.... - 然后呢？
-And.... -And?
你倒是说啊！
Speak, will you?!
她出出卖了我们，她说了费金和奥立弗的名字
She peached. She told him Fagin had OIiver.
老头要去找条子，就是今天晚上
And the old man was to go to the traps. Now, tonight.
- 让我走，让我出去！ - 比尔！比尔！一句话！
-Let me go. Let me out! -Bill! Bill! A word--
- 别跟我说话，现在不安全！ - 听我说一句话！
-Don't speak to me, it's not safe! -Hear me speak a word!
比尔，你不会....
Bill, you won't be....
你不会太过分吧，比尔?
You won't be too violent, Bill?
快走，孩子们，快走！
FIit, boys, flit!
你们还没说出斯皮达菲 那些条子就要来到门口啦
The traps will be at the door afore you can say "Spitalfields."
快逃！快逃！快逃！
FIit! FIit! FIit!
逃！
FIit!
走
Come on.
是你啊
Oh, it's you.
比尔？
Bill?
什么事？
What's the matter?
比尔，为什么这样看着我？
Bill, why do you Iook Iike that at me?
这点亮光够我办事了
There's enough Iight for what I've gotta do.
我，我做了什么啊？
What--? What have I done?
- 告诉我 - 你心里明白
-Speak to me. -You know.
你今晚被人看到了
You was watched tonight.
你说的每个字都被听到了
Every word you said was heard.
我，我没说你的名字，比尔
I-- I never said your name, Bill.
从来没有
Never.
比尔，比尔，比尔！
Bill. Bill. Bill!
噢，上帝，噢，上帝啊，饶了我吧！
Oh, God. Oh, God, have mercy!
南希？
Nance?
我什么都没有做
I haven't done nothing.
走开，走开啊你
Go on, be off with you.
你好，老费
Hello, Fagey.
你好啊，孩子们
Hello, Iads.
有什么消息吗，托比？有没有消息？
What's the news, Toby? What's the news?
我这儿有，费金，都在报纸上了
I have it here, Fagin. It's all in The Chronicle.
有你的名字，有比尔的，还有奥立弗的
You're in it. Bill's in it. OIiver's in it.
报纸？
The Chronicle?
想想啊，你出名了，费金
Fancy that. You're famous, Fagin.
读来听听
Read it.
发生在斯皮达菲的那宗谋杀案...
"More information has reached your correspondent...
...极其邪恶残忍，使所有伦敦市民...
...concerning the foul and bestial murder...
...感到震惊和恐惧，关于此案...
...that took place in Spitalfields and which has shocked and appalled...
...本报记者获得了更多信息
...the citizens of London.
据信，受害者是一名年轻女子...
It is believed that the victim, a young woman...
...其姓名确认为南希...
...now identified as Nancy...
...为暴力致死...
...was brutally beaten to death...
...凶手为威廉・塞克斯...
...by one William Sykes...
...此人生性残暴，市民早有所闻
...a well-known, dangerous villain.
杀人动机仍未查明...
The motive is as yet unclear...
...本报记者获悉...
...but your correspondent has Iearned that the murdered woman...
...受害者曾表示...
...had informed on her associate...
...自己与臭名昭著的费金并无瓜葛...
...and on an infamous fence, Fagin...
...后者因诱拐名为奥立弗・忒斯特的儿童 而被警方通缉
...who is now wanted for the abduction of a young boy, OIiver Twist.
费金和塞克斯均未归案...
Neither Fagin nor Sykes are presently in custody...
...但警方已着手缉拿行动...
...but the police are engaged in searching for them...
...在城内外搜寻
...throughout the city and beyond.
据警方称，塞克斯...
Sykes, according to the police...
...通常以一条白色烈犬相伴
...is usually accompanied by a fierce white dog."
怎么样？
How about that, eh?
来，回来
Come. Come back here.
我们回伦敦去
We're going back to London.
我要跟别人说了
I'II have people to speak to.
我要找费金要点钱，再到法国去
I'II force shiners out of Fagin, get to France.
妈的，我们拼了
Damn me, we'II risk it.
他干了什么事？
Who's he done in?
- 他们说，他们说是个女的 - 他害了一个女的？
-They say-- They say it's a woman. -He's done in a woman?
大牛
Bullseye.
你没听到我吹口哨吗？
Don't you hear me when I whistle?
你聋了吗？
You gone deaf or something?
过来，快
Come here. Come on.
我不会害你，过来，过来，大牛
I ain't gonna harm you. Come on. Come on, Bullseye.
来这儿
Come here.
别咬了，我警告你
Stop it! I'm warning you.
松口，我不是跟你玩
Let go, I ain't playing with you!
松口啊，你这臭东西！
Let it go, you stinking varmint!
大牛！
Bullseye!
大牛，大牛
Bullseye. Bullseye.
回来，回来
Get back here. Get back here.
妈的！
Damn it!
看，这是他的狗
Look, it's his dog.
就是他的狗！
It's his dog!
过来，孩子
Here, boy.
- 来这 - 别靠近它
-Here. -Don't go near him.
有个孩子情况很危险，布拉瑟斯检察长...
There is a child in danger, Inspector BIathers...
...可是你现在好像只对...
...but you only seem interested...
...威廉・塞克斯这个人感兴趣
...in apprehending this man, William Sykes.
你应该多关心一下...
Your concern should be...
- ...那孩子的安危啊 - 让我说句话...
-...for the safety of the boy. -AIIow me to say...
...我们平时就是这样办事的
...this is our usual way of doing business.
我是这样想的
My thinking is this:
如果我们逮到了塞克斯，费金就逃不掉了
If we get Sykes, we get Fagin.
- 如果我们逮住了费金 - 我说
-And if we get Fagin-- -Look.
长官，找到那条狗了
Sir, we found the dog.
我们就在这里等着条子来抓吗？
Are we going to sit here waiting for the traps to find us?
- 闭嘴 - 不，他说的没错
-Shut it. -No, he's right.
我们得再逃远点
We should do another flit.
是条子！
The traps!
什么？
What?
是他
It's him.
- 别让他进来 - 肯定要
-Don't Iet him in. -We must.
去啊
Go on.
去啊！
Go on!
给我们留点火啊
Don't Ieave us in the dark.
你们都是混蛋
Damn you all.
没话跟我说吗？
Have you nothing to say to me?
- 你到这里来太不安全了，比尔 - 对你不安全，对我安全
-Not safe for you to stop here, Bill. -If it's safe for you, it's safe for me.
那个…
Is it...?
尸体埋了吗？
The body, is it buried?
机灵鬼，快让他进来
Dodger, Iet him in quick.
机灵鬼
Dodger.
照我说的做
Do as I say.
别靠近我，你这个怪物
Don't come near me, you monster.
你们都在这作证，我不怕他
You're my witnesses. I'm not afraid of him.
如果他们来要人，我不会保他
And if they come here after him, I'II give him up.
我会告诉他们你在这里
I'II tell them you're here.
他要杀我随他便，但是 只要我在这，我就会告发他
He may kill me if he Iikes, but if I'm here, I'II give him up.
就算他被活活烫死，我也要告发
If he was to be boiled alive, so I would.
你这个小…
Why, you Iittle--
放开我！
Get off me!
看我把你撕开几块！
Or I'II tear you Iimb from Iimb!
救命，他在这里！
Help, he's here!
- 他在这里，把门撞开！ - 在上面的窗边
-He's here. Break down the door! -Up at the window!
救命！上来啊，求求你们
Help! Come up, please!
- 那个就是比尔・塞克斯！ - 滚你们的！
-That's Bill Sykes! -Damn you all!
随你们怎么办！我还是不服输！
Do your worst. I'II cheat you yet!
不，比尔，不要，我们留着他还有用
No! Bill, no. He's our bargaining tool.
不是你的，费金，是我的
Not yours, Fagin. Mine.
比尔！
Bill!
别开枪
Don't fire.
- 别开枪 - 不要开枪，伙计们
-Don't fire. -Hold your fire, men.
- 别开枪 - 放开那孩子！
-Hold your fire. -I'II Iet the boy go.
我会让他掉下去
I'II Iet him drop.
不要乱来，否则我松手了！
Don't try nothing, or I'II Iet him go!
上来
Get up there.
过去，过去
Cross, cross.
上去！上去
Up there. Up there.
抓住那里，抓住
Grab hold of there. Grab hold of it.
长官，我们追吧
We must give chase, sir.
下来
Get down.
他们要逃了！
They're getting away!
在那儿，在那儿！
There, there. There he is!
抓住他！抓住他！
Get him! Get him!
妈的！
Damn it!
抓住
Grab it.
抓住！
Grab it!
奥立弗？
OIiver?
OIiver!
奥立弗？
- 他在这，先生 - 过来，孩子
-Here he is, sir. -Come along, my boy.
格林维格先生有话要跟你说
Mr. Grimwig has something to say to you.
招呼一下，贝德温太太
Do the honors, Mrs. Bedwin.
现在，孩子，我承认错怪你了
Now then, young man, I confess I misjudged you.
说真的，我还怕你的恩人要我吃掉我的头呢
Truth to tell, I feared your benefactor would make me eat my head.
不过他是我的好朋友，他原谅了我
But he's a good friend and has pardoned me.
- 这个给你，奥立弗 - 谢谢，先生
-And one for OIiver. -Thank you, sir.
- 那么… - 你也来一杯,贝德温太太
-So-- -And you too, Mrs. Bedwin.
- 我不知道是否规矩，先生 - 你一定要喝
-I don't know as I should, sir. -You must.
请允许我借此机会敬你一杯
So I'II take the Iiberty, if you'II allow me, to salute you.
- 萨姆・沃特斯 - 是奥立弗・忒斯特
-To Sam Waters. -OIiver Twist.
对，奥立弗・忒斯特，敬奥立弗・忒斯特
OIiver Twist. To OIiver Twist.
对
Yes.
怎么啦，奥立弗，孩子，怎么啦？
Why, OIiver. My child, what's the matter?
为什么那么难过？
Why are you so sad?
你确定要这样做吗？
Are you certain, OIiver, you wish to go through with this?
是的，先生
Yes, sir.
我确定
Certain.
谁？
Yes?
这位小先生也一起来吗？
Is the young gentleman to come too, sir?
这里不适合小孩子看，先生
It's not a sight for children, sir.
当然不适合，朋友，但是这个小孩...
It is not indeed, my friend. But this child has seen this man...
...见过那个人的起起落落
...in the full career of his success and villainy.
这也是他的愿望，就算会留下痛苦和恐惧...
And it is his wish, even at the cost of some pain and fear...
...他也要看看他
...that he should see him now.
十八
Eighteen.
喂！
Hey!
好孩子
Good boy.
好孩子，查理
Good boy, Charley.
做得好
Well done.
好样儿的，查理，做得好，做得好
Good boy, Charley, well done. Well done.
- 带着孩子去睡吧 - 不要害怕
-Take the boy away to bed. -Don't be frightened.
费金
Fagin.
我是，我就是这个老头，大人
That's me. An old man, my Iord.
糟…糟老头
A-- A very old-- OId man.
有人想看看你
Someone here wants to see you.
- 打啊！打死他们！ - 别害怕
-Strike! Strike them all dead! -Easy.
为什么他们可以宰掉我？
What right have they to butcher me?
跟他说吧，请你快些
Speak to him now. Quick, if you please.
因为他越来越不行了
For he grows worse as the time goes on.
费金，你对我很好
Fagin, you were kind to me.
是的，是的
Yes, yes.
我以后还会好
I'II be kind again.
- 我不怕 - 奥立弗！
-I'm not afraid. -OIiver!
我…想和你说句悄悄话
Let-- Let me whisper to you.
你记得那个箱子吗，奥立弗？
You remember the box, OIiver?
装满了老头子的好东西，奥立弗？
With my pretty things for my old age, OIiver?
我把它藏在前厅的烟囱上了
It's hid a Iittle way up the chimney in the top front room.
留给你，奥立弗
It's yours, OIiver.
- 你的，但是我们要说说话 - 是的，是的
-Yours, but we must talk. -Yes, yes.
我们先祷告一下好吗？
But shall we say a prayer together first?
请你
Do.
就做一次，和我一起跪下来 ...
Say only one, upon your knees, with me...
...做完我们谈一个早上都行
...and we can talk all morning.
出去，出去
Outside. Outside.
你可以说我睡着了，他们会相信你的
You can say I've gone to sleep. They'II believe you.
你把我弄出去，那些好东西都是你的 亲爱的，全是你的
You can get me out. The pretty things are yours, my dear, yours.
- 噢，上帝啊，饶恕这个可怜的人吧 - 没错，没错
-Oh, God, forgive this wretched man. -That's right, that's right.
这样对我们有好处
That will help us on.
如果…如果…如果…我
If-- If-- If-- If I...
...上绞刑架的时候摇摇晃晃
...shake and tremble as we pass the gallows, don't-- Don't--
你，你别介意，快点走，快，快，快
Don't you mind, hurry on. Now, now, now.
- 你还有什么对他说吗？ - 没有了
-Have you more to say to him, sir? -Nothing more.
- 你最好别管他 - 快点，快点，快点
-You'd better Ieave him. -Press on, press on, press on.
快点，快点
Press on, press on.
轻点，轻点，不，不要！
Softly. Softly. No, no!
好痛！
It hurts!
快点，快点！
Faster, faster!
快点，快点，快点，快点！
Faster, faster, faster, faster!